So hello everyone and welcome to a new
episode of Sahaj Times podcast. My name
is Lele. I'm the host of this podcast
and right now today is the 27th of July
and what has just happened is that the
OAC's came back. They're doing their new
tour. They they're coming back. They're
together again. And guess who else is
together again after two months of
shooting episodes really far from each
other, not together with other guests,
but without any co-host beside Roita
that helped me at once. Fabri,
>> how's life?
>> It's us.
>> Very good. Very happy to be back. I
missed you.
>> Okay, cool.
I don't know. I feel like masculine
enough, you know, toxic masculine enough
to say that it's fine. You you could
keep it that for yourself.
>> I am manly enough to say that I missed
you
>> because you are a father and I can't
wait for you to bring some fatherhood
into this episode.
>> Talking about kids,
>> talking about fatherhood, some Yoda
quotes. And so Fabri, how how are how
are you?
>> Life is good. So mentioning mentioning
so today I'm in a funy mood. I'm just
going to tell you to begin with. I'm
just going to disturb you and and and
mess around the entire one hour. That's
I spend two weeks with my kids. I'm on
holidays. So I'm I'm in teenage mode.
I'm just one of them. My my poor wife
has with three kids at home. Uh so the
first thing that came to mind is this. I
did this really cool episode with Romina
two weeks ago. Whoever didn't see it, go
see it on SG marriages because today is
a bit of a continuation of that. And
then we had very little views, right?
And then I'm like, oh, it's July, it's
holiday. Then what happens is the next
week Le does the episode on mental
health and he has a lot of views. And I
got so annoyed at that. like absolutely
mega annoyed at that situation
and I can see from your smile that
you're very satisfied about the
situation.
>> Actually, I don't even know what are you
talking about because if we if we
actually talk about the views, they were
more or less the same if you actually go
and check. But we're not doing this this
for the views. We're doing this because
I don't know, we want to make someone's
day a little bit better and to give some
sahaj entertainment and also a little
bit of teachings even though I'm not in
the position to teach anything but I
think a lot which is my unbalanced
position can bring me can help me to do
a s podcast to question and think
>> and what am I thinking about
>> teachings
>> what are we thinking about so since it's
July we are approaching the marriages
and every single year things happen
during the marriages and I feel like in
general it gets like I don't know people
go to the marriages if you put your name
down with a little bit of something like
in your chest you know there is like a
little bit of a pain a little bit of
stress little bit of anxiety because of
course you don't know what is going to
happen and that happens with every
single step in our lives. But actually
for this month, for this series of of
episodes, we would like to bring some
some stories, some guests and some
experiences that maybe can help people
to live this process in a lighter way,
in a little bit of better way, and maybe
in a more successful way for the future.
because you might already know what
might happen to you, especially if it's
like your first time putting your name
down or if it's like your first time in
a relationship. There is going to be a
marriage. Now, it's not easy. Like, we
were born with this idea, but it's not
easy because that's your first
relationship. You don't know how to
behave for many people. You don't know
how to behave in certain situations. And
you have to also learn from other people
that have been there before you. And who
is today's guest Fabri?
>> Especially we can learn from those that
have been with Shimar I would say on
this on this topic who married during
that time and got nice advice. So today
uh we can do a little game. I can say
I'm sure that if I'm going to say the
profile of the person and many of the
people are going to guess who with this
>> okay let's play this game.
>> It's a very sweet auntie. She's from the
UK. She got her sufferization in 79 in
India.
Uh 3 years later in 82 she got married
which by today's standards would be
speed of light right imagine somebody
comes and sin 3 years after they get
married. uh the family lived uh
sometimes in Vancouver
uh now in UK and by now I'm sure that
most of the people already kind of get
the idea but this specific last item
will give away the name because auntie
has five kids.
So by now everybody is screaming payment
family. So welcome to Auntie Felicity.
>> Hello auntie. Let me fix this. Hello J
Shimati.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you so much for having me. It's a
very special honor to be on your
beautiful, beautiful podcast that you
do.
Oh, I um
Yes. You were saying about 3 years after
realization getting married. Well, I
should tell you that my husband had only
had his realization for three months.
No way.
>> Yes.
>> Classic those times though.
>> Yes. Very Yes. Everything was very
speeded up in those days, you know. So
that was pretty amazing. Yeah.
>> So when when you met him, it was still
learning the
>> I know. And that was one of the things
after we got married and we went back to
England for a while and I said, "Oh,
let's go foot soak." And he went, "Oh,
what? Really? No.
>> What is it?"
>> What is soap?
>> And then I went, "Oh, right. He's only
just got realization like three months
ago, you know. So, he's not necessarily
into that habit. So, yeah, that was that
was an in it was a very interesting
thing. But we're skipping ahead a bit.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. You go first.
>> Yeah, we can skip a little bit even
though it was interesting. I didn't know
that auntie but so can I ask you just to
start then we can see where we go. Can
you tell us your experience with saj
marriages with what did shimadi tell you
and just tell us tell us like you're
free to go no no no no no limits
>> yeah so so I so I would say was from
like 198081
she was preparing us for marriages we
were a small collective um I guess maybe
we had like 40 50 in England at that
point point I can't remember the exact
year it was either 8081 no it must have
been 80 no it was 80 um and we were we
were in Shimadichi's apartment in
Victoria Gardens and she was sitting
with her back to the window often she
sat in that position and she was just
sort of talking about more m mundane
things she you conversations would just
sometimes, you know, she'd be talking
about curtains or, you know, not always
so-called deep things. She would keep
the conversations going and talk to us
so that we could sit there, absorb her
vibrations and clear, you know,
>> every minute in her presence was like
you were being worked on. your your
chakras, your emotions, your thoughts,
everything, you know, it was like
>> total workout.
>> Um, and in those days there was a lot
working out in all of us cuz we'd only
just come into Sajoga. So, it could be
very painful sometimes. Anyway, so she
was just I just I don't remember the
conversation
and then suddenly the atmosphere changed
and it was like it got very you felt
this depth and importance and she said
to us you are the foundation stones on
which I'm building the sajoga my vision.
>> Wow. And she said, "But I am sending you
the children and they are the ones that
are going to change the world. And I'm
not saying this to put pressure on
anybody at all. I'm just saying that
this is how important the marriages
were." And she said, and she actually
said at that point, everyone was pretty
well, mostly under 30. There was two
couples who'd come into Sajoga already
married.
>> Yeah. And she said if you don't have
children if you're not going no she said
if you're not going to get married you
can get out of sajoka that's that's what
she said. So you know right from that
point we understood okay this is our
job. This is our job to help support
Shumalachi to fulfill her vision and
change the spirituality and humanity of
the world.
And so then I would say sort of fast
forward and the following year this
young couple came uh to her I can
remember in the ashram in Dallas Hill
and they must have just you know been
chatting and being friendly and they
said oh sharaji we'd like to get
married. So at this point there had been
no marriages. Oh, maybe one. There was
one young woman who So there was one
young woman at mother married to an
Indian and we all went lucky her she's
married to an Indian you know it was a
disaster within like two three days and
they showered her with jewels and all
these lovely things you know that
Indians do but within three days nope it
was finished no mother said no that's
not going to work for you and and and
that
>> was like oh okay it's not the be all and
end all of everything you know and So I
would say those early three years before
I got married there was so many dramas
and situations that mother created to
work out all our conditioning. So you
know so this was one of them and we had
this saying there but for the grace of
God go I that something is happening to
that person this week it could be me
next week. So I would say we were very
supportive of each other you know it
wasn't like oh what's wrong with that
person you know mother's telling them
off. wasn't like that. It was just like
okay hearts.
>> Yeah, this is happening and it was much
more like a big family and there were no
secrets at all. Shadaji would talk about
everything amongst us. So that we
learned from each other. We learned from
each other's mistakes. We learned for
the good things you know and and she
would just use whoever she thought she
should use to to test to test us all.
So this young couple came and they said
so I'm hope these things that I'm
sharing will give some perspective and
background you know because people
sometimes go oh you were so lucky
Shimati was with you you know you knew
she match so I want to explain that it
was a little bit more complex than that
and that things haven't changed that
much from then
>> um so I hope you know some of these
examples will will help that
>> um and so that then young people will
have a little bit more confidence you
know in themselves. So this young couple
came and I remember I was sitting there
we were all together in Dalis Ashram and
Jimi said to them um will it make you
happy and they said oh yes mother yes.
So fast forward, they get married.
Another disaster.
Um his own different cultures. One was
one was Greek, one was English.
Different expectations, conditionings.
Um some other things that I won't
mention, you know, it's not fair.
>> But it just, you know, fell apart. Uh I
mean, mother tried, you know, she she
made suggestions. She actually at one
point um got someone to make the husband
buy a present for the wife, you know,
like this was a you know she did I can't
remember but she did different things
you know and then and then finally she
said okay okay that's it it's over
>> and she said to them you know
I said to you will it make you happy and
they and they said you know oh but
mother You said you know it will make us
happy. She goes but that wasn't the
point.
>> The point is marriage is for joy
>> not for happiness you know it's deeper
than that. It's much deeper than that.
It's to give you joy you know. So
suddenly our attention went from this
more superficial level of marriage to
okay this is different and that was a
big wakeup call. I mean I I can remember
going you know it was just something
very deep that went into us and then
other after that there were a couple of
like Morin. So Morin was a lovely
example. Shumati did say you know if you
find somebody outside of Sajoga you know
bring them in bring them in
>> and she was at college and her husband
her now husband was also at college and
met her and wanted to marry her. So she
did it really nicely. She brought him to
to Shadaji you know this he wants to
marry me um she was detached from it you
know she didn't have any whatever you
say mother you know she was surrendered
>> he's going to force it
>> yeah and Shrimati said no no he's born
realized
>> very good so they so they then had a
marriage there were two marriages and I
can't remember the second I apologize
that my memory is not as accurate but
what I do remember properly I will say
but if I can't I I will say I can't. So
um so so we had a this was a beautiful
wedding and I know that they've talked
about their their wedding already. So
then fast forward later on I I think I
can't remember if it was anyway it's 81
Shrimadaji
starts to have I think Pat anyway
doesn't matter but then we started
having more collective marriages first
there was a couple of marriages together
then at Chelsham road there was two sets
of collective marriages one was like 16
couples
and then there was another batch of of
marriages And it was really it was a
really a huge move forward that suddenly
you know the collective had grown a lot.
There was now by 81 it was spread into
Europe. So we had Italians and Swiss and
you know all these European countries
had come in. So there was a bigger pool
of yogis for mother you know to choose
>> and in general she was suggesting and
matching and saying oh you know try
this. Um one couple had come in together
but then separated and then Shimaraji
said later to the husband to the you
know the the yogi maybe you know you
should marry ask her ask her if she
would like. So it's very important to
understand there was always choice.
There was always choice and if you
didn't feel comfortable you weren't have
he that's fine. There was no mother
didn't make a big deal about it at all.
Okay that's fine. We'll find you someone
else or I have someone else in mind. She
also talked a lot about the men getting
married because they were catching on
left Nabby. She would say ah you need to
get married left Ni catch we'll settle
you down
>> you know so so it was always the
attention was on the vibrations of the
marriage and and I think when d when the
first couple had that not happy marriage
shei explained now I'm remembering she
explained she said when you get married
you said
you should be matched vibrationally.
So you balance each other.
>> Yeah.
>> And she she said this again later on.
She says, "I match you for vibrations,
for your evolution, for your spiritual
growth. I match you so that you know you
have balance together to grow together."
And it was interesting because there
were a couple of couples who
um chose themselves
and went and shamadi you know so
Shamadaji in her motherly graciousness
is very rare for her to say no. She
would only say if you had already
decided you would like to do this. She
would just go along with it. If you came
to her and you were detached and
surrendered, is this a good idea? And
you'd have to be completely surrendered
and detached. Then she would give you an
honest answer.
>> Yeah. you know and and um so so one or
two of those couples who match
themselves actually went out of sajoga
and you could see and I think mother
talked about it you know they were
attracted to you know either they were
both a bit leftsided so
>> there similarities
matched by similarity
>> yeah and then they support each other's
weaknesses and and then it just you know
negativity works and and took them out
of yoga. So,
>> and then you spin out. Exactly.
>> Yeah. Then you spin out. That's right.
So, then I guess we could So, I'll just
share a little bit about
So, there were a lot of little dramas,
you know, there was one gentleman that
mother suggested a match and he said,
"Oh, no, no." So, she said, "Okay." So
then she found six in succession six
different yoginies
um to marry and they all said no they
all said no no I don't want to be
married to him and f so finally he said
okay I better marry the first one who
was happy to marry me you know
>> I go back to it
>> yeah and you could see it was a very
nice match it was a very nice match but
but that's the point we so we had little
tests before we got. And so for myself
personally,
um I had this I'll just share quickly. I
had this one brother. I would go down to
this collective and visit which I really
enjoyed. And as the marriages were
coming up, um you know, they'd say,
"Okay, we're going to have marriages
now." And it was happened very quickly,
like within a period of two weeks. And
some people would come and say, you
know, I'd like to marry so and so,
mother. Um uh that was another match
that didn't work out. I remember um and
Shimani would start making suggestions
you know go and ask and see if they're
happy with that and one of the brothers
said to me who was completely a platonic
brother oh I don't know if I should
marry you or so and so I was really
shocked because this had you know wasn't
in my attention at all I was I was
actually waiting I was so relieved that
Shamataji was going to
>> you know pick someone for me that I
didn't have to think about it anymore. I
didn't have to because I knew I you know
when you look at someone you see the
outside of them.
>> You you you really don't know all the
subtleties and complexities that's going
on inside and you when you get married
then you find out about all those things
and for me I just thought I can't see
the depth of a person you know traumati
does. So I was really relieved that I
wouldn't have to that was one
responsibility off my back. I didn't
have to think about that anymore.
>> And so anyway, so this young man and I
just thought I don't know what to do
with this. You know, it was really like
bothering me and I didn't know if he was
going to follow it through and I didn't
feel comfortable. And that was the week
we had a seminar in Dorset. And I
happened to be in the car with Shamatagi
and
I just and I it was in my attention that
I want to give this to Mala. I just I
want to get rid of this. And we were in
the car and it went very quiet. No one
was talking. And I was sitting behind
her and suddenly I felt this is my
moment. And I just very humbly said,
"Oh, Shma, you know, so and so said to
me he didn't know whether he should
marry me or this girl." And I just left
it like that.
>> So
>> didn't say anything completely like, you
know, I give this to you mother. And she
just was quiet for a while. And then she
said, "You should marry someone who who
will talk to you, who you can talk to."
And I just went, "Okay, done. Finished."
You know, which was very sweet. It was
very sweet. And I thought, "Yeah, I
guess it would be nice to be married."
Because he was very quiet, this guy. He
was Aquarius and it was kind of a bit up
in the air there, you know. I mean, I
wasn't on my radar at all. I was not
looking at anyone like that at all, you
know. Yes.
>> So then um so then within a day or two
Shimaraji so they were we were having
this seminar and I remember in the
afternoon that people were Shamaraji was
suggesting people to to be matched and
she suddenly said ah Felicity should
marry so and so
and I suddenly felt very shocked because
I realized
that I'd never this this this very
lovely deep yogi who I knew was lovely
and deep but he did not look like I
suddenly realized I had an expectation
of what my husband was going to look
like which was kind of tall and and well
I guess I should say handsome how but I
wasn't
>> I hadn't it wasn't conscious it wasn't a
conscious thing and I went oh my
goodness I didn't know you thought that
what you know and and so then it got
very confusing and I you know I'm going
ah I don't you know I don't understand
this why why is this a good match but I
trusted Shumati so I just said to myself
I'm not going to think about this at all
I I Chumataraji you show me why this is
a good match please show me so I can
understand why this is a good match and
in my heart I I said this and so two
days passed the third morning as I was
waking up I suddenly had this vision of
being with this this yogi and I felt
completely calm and contentment and
companionship. I thought, "Oh, marriage
is supposed to be friendship and
companionable. It's not this sort of
emotional roller coaster, a big thing
that you sort of grow up with in the
media that you meet the one and it's
going to be oh, you know, it's not like
that. It's much more level
>> and you're sort of balanced and you make
friends and and then I could feel the
love within that kind of deeper
relationship, you know, how the depth
would grow, the love would grow. And I
thought, "Oh, oh, that's what marriage
is about." And it felt so nice. And
then, as it turned out, after a few
days, I hadn't heard anything. And I
said to her mother, you know, "Oh, I
just was wondering." She goes, "Oh, no,
no, no. He doesn't want to marry you.
It's fine." like that, you know,
>> it was your test to
>> go. Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. You know, so
>> so we all had, you know, little
situations and things like that that
mother was working these things through
us. And then there was another instance
um we were at we were at we were at a
puja in Brighton. We were preparing for
the puja and I wasn't feeling good in
myself. I I couldn't seem I felt like I
must help but at the same time I was
feeling like I need to sit down. I'm not
feeling balanced, you know, but yes, I
should go and help, you know, and I was
really in this kind of oh and I just
stood outside mother's door just to kind
of try and settle myself, you know, and
then the door opened and she said, "What
is it? What's up with you? Come on in."
You know, so so I came in and I sat in
front of her. I knelt in front you know
and as I was there the other people
who'd been in the room left and it was
just me and Shimadaji which was wasn't
usual you know and I'm just sitting
there she's so sweet and so she would
start talking about some things you know
she would often she would talk about
things to take my attention off myself
so I wouldn't be you know just and
suddenly she started talking about this
married couple. It was a both Indian.
One had come specially from India. The
other was already um in England but not
but not um not raised in England. So
very different cultures.
[Music]
And she started to say to me, she
started to complain about,
well, not complain, she started to tell
me that the wife had been complaining a
lot about her husband, had been saying
this about him and that about him and,
you know, and she was saying, "What do
you think? What do you think about
this?" You know, is this is this okay?
Is this okay? You know, and and I
remember because I always I never want
to say anything bad about anybody, you
know. So I'm just not saying anything,
but she pushes at you. This is your
test, you see. So she pushes at you
because she wants you to answer. She
wants to know, you know, and so finally,
and I could sort of feel obviously the
way she's saying all this, this is not
okay. You should not be doing this, you
know, you should not be complaining to
other people, period. Or even
criticizing your husband.
>> And and I just said, uh, oh no, you
know, do you think this is okay? You
know, she'd lean forward. Do you think
this is okay? Is this good? you know and
and I said oh no no no humanity no you
know and it was very and I felt like
mother's telling me this for a reason
this is a lesson that I must learn you
know
>> um and I didn't think of myself as a
judgmental or critical person you know
that wasn't my concept of myself
>> but anyway I I you know I thought oh
this is important this is important I
have to remember this you know so so I
think in context of that I'll fast
forward to after we were married and so
I'll go back and say the story of our
marriage because it was quite unusual it
was quite unusual
>> but so the day after we were married we
so that year we all got married and I'll
tell more details and then Shimaraji
booked hotels she got them to book a
hotel for the married couples to go to
the night of the marriage you know
>> oh wow
>> yes oh wow Wow, that's what I thought.
Oh, wow. You know, and and so we but so
we spent the night. I think it was
because she was really trying to help us
bond together as couples, you know,
>> space.
>> Yes. And to give you some space to, you
know, be together. And it was really
sweet. He he told he told me all about
his home and his friends and you know
you really could get a feeling in a in a
personal space together away from the
collective which was always sort of
impeding into your conscious
>> and it was very sweet. And then in the
morning, all the couples were having
breakfast together at separate little
tables of two people opposite each
other. And he wasn't really talking very
much, which was a relief to me because I
was a big talker. And it was a big
relief that I didn't
>> He was a good listener.
>> Yeah.
Was very nice. And so we were just
sitting there in companionable silence
eating our breakfast. And suddenly into
my head came all these judgmental
thoughts like oh he's doing this like it
was like some kind of boot thing you
know it just like jumped on me and it
was so strong and it wanted to say to
him why are you doing this why are you
doing that you know and I remembered
this experience with mother and I
thought she was trying to save me from
this you know and I literally just
closed my mouth
>> like this and I thought don't open your
mouth don't say anything cuz I could
feel It's like it just wanted to jump
out at him and and I was very conscious
that, you know, that we were in this
special place together. We just got
married and that you have to create this
beautiful loving relationship together
and that doesn't belong anywhere. That's
not going to, you know, do anything at
all.
>> Attitude. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, I just can't explain how
grateful I was that I'd had that
experience, you know.
>> Absolutely. And so I just shut up. I
didn't say anything. It was like, "No,
I'm not going to say anything at all."
And then it just went away. You know,
maybe it went off to another table and
tried it at somebody.
>> The next couple next
>> just sort of left left me alone. And I
just remember going, "Oh, thank
goodness." you know like okay we get but
it was such a strong experience that I
think it made me really be on alert you
know to not allow critical thoughts you
know to come in or judgmental thoughts
to come in and I think and I'll add to
this story because this is the right
place um many years later I think so I
was in England on my own because I'd
brought my son to be part of the
collective and go to the Sahage school.
So this must have been like 88, 1988
and I was at the end of the visit and I
was going back to Canada and I went at
the end of a puja or program or
something and I went to say goodbye to
Shrimat. I was going back and she was
you know very sweet. Okay. Yes. Yes. And
then she said and how's your husband? So
I have to say in my ego
>> I obviously at that point still had some
like you know well he does this and he
does that you know
>> and I said I said you know I have to
absolutely pull my ears and I said to
her in a very you know light way
>> oh um his ego is much better now mother
and she just lit into me. She was just
like, "Oh, you English, what is the
matter with you? Why are you so
critical? Why can't you?" And she said,
and she mentions someone else and she
goes, "Oh, you're just like so and so,
you know, she's terrible like that." And
then she said to me, "Why can't you just
love him?"
>> And I just went, "Okay, Shrimati G."
>> Wow.
>> That was my answer, you know. So, I
really want to share that. This is not
just for me. This is for all of us. This
is how we should be, you know. She
wanted us to enjoy each other to be
light and to be joyful and happy. And
interestingly at that same puja
um we had a new leader she changed the
leaders in Canada and that's one of the
reasons I was going back you know I at
that time I thought this is this is a
good change and he came to me and I must
have said you know yeah I'm coming back
and he said to me you know what
Shamadaji just told me she said to me
because the previous leader had been
extremely critical and very divisive in
her criticisms and and constantly
throwing people out of the collective
because, oh, they're too left-sided or
they're this and that. And he said, she
said to me, allow the negativity to come
up and be exposed and don't pay
attention to it. I'm working it out. And
I thought, wow. And I think I always
felt after that that that's also in
marriage, you know, that you have to
that we're on a journey together. When
you're married, you're on a journey
together. You are separate people on
separate spiritual paths, different
rates or evolution. Not rates, but you
know, going through different things,
but but yes, different stages, but you
were also together, you know, like you
were saying, the wheels of the chariot,
you know, you're together, but you're on
different paths. And I learned that it's
not for us to judge and criticize. It's
very easy to see in the other partner
things that aren't like you. And in the
beginning, you think,
>> "Oh, why is he doing that? Why why is
that happening?" Um, and in your
innocence and your inexperience, you can
think, "Oh, that's wrong." You know,
>> but it's not. It's just different.
>> It's just different. And if you
so
that really helped me to let go of that
feeling that you're responsible for
their growth. You're not.
>> It's nothing to do with you. It's
completely between them and Shimati, you
know, and
>> they often they will meditate, you know.
So my husband meditated differently in
that we would sit in meditation.
He liked to just be mostly quiet and
just to be quiet. At that time when we
were first married I was very used to
doing mantras you know putting on
mother's talks because I had a lot of
thoughts and thinking this helped me to
be you know quiet and I just but I
remember sort of feeling like oh is he
really meditating you know is he going
deep but that's not for me to decide.
You can't you can't see the depth of
another person really only Shimati can
you know and so I've got a little off
track here but yeah but I think there's
a really important point one thing that
came to my mind actually because I've
seen to myself also
sometimes your husband and wife or
spouse could also be off but the other
thing is also these are things that you
need to work within the family and
criticizing publicly your spouse even in
a joking way. This is what I learned
because Italians they like to tell jokes
and stories and and sometimes, you know,
my wife is like, you know, you make me
look like a goofy cartoon character all
the time, you know, like because I like
to make fun stories and and I had to
learn that because
your relationship is so sacred within
the marriage between you and Shrimar and
your spouse that even if there is a
problem, it is really not your place to
share it unless I I'm getting beaten up.
All right, fine. Then you go talk to the
leader and you fix something, right? But
and and I had this story, very
interesting story. So my best friend, of
course, Le is also my best friend, but
my best friend of my
his name is Andrea from Rome. He's
married to Janag, which is one of my
favorite sister in the world. We have a
common chat of the families. Uh, so we
we and because my wife doesn't speak
Italian, usually is Andrea and I and
Janaki. So, you know, it's it's it's
it's it's
not fair, you know, we continuously
pulling her leg right and left, right
and left. And I remember there was a
month that we really did it a lot. and
uh and and it's very innocent jokes. You
know, you send these little memes or the
Instagram videos of the wife uh getting
too angry about things and the husband
is like, "Okay, just calm down, honey."
And she goes completely crazy because
you say, "Calm down." Right. Like small
things like this. Nothing, you know,
crazy. But it was a bit continuous for a
month.
>> And I remember that
>> you got into the fun of it.
>> Exactly. And again it is in a way
innocent but it is not if it is so long.
>> And uh and I had this dream what that
night I go to sleep and uh basically we
are in this um
in this big table. Shimaji is at the
other the table and there's all sorts of
yogis and Andre and Janaki are there.
and my wife are there and again Andrea
and I are looking at each other smiling
making a little joke about Janicki or
being about my wife this and that waving
a ball you know we're laughing and then
at some point I do a second or a third
joke I don't remember what and Shini
just looks like uh that's enough now and
then in a very sweet joyful way she
start making jokes about me and
everybody and everybody at the table is
laughing like crazy and I I actually I
didn't mind at all because she she did
it in such a sweet way, beautiful way,
joy. I was part of the joke, but also it
made me understand how does it feel now
that you're on the other side, right?
>> Yes.
>> And and it was very sweet. It was very
beautiful. But
>> I also got the message. So the next day
actually I text Janeki like Janicki I'm
so sorry you know for this Monday you
know because there is that sacredness
about your spouse about your marriage
>> and is within God and and again even
light jokes they had to be measured this
is something I learned from my wife I
feel she really she really uh taught me
that and you know I
>> well it's it's also I mean humor is very
important in the marriage and and I I
mean it's interesting because I'm from
England And the, you know, when I was in
the collective there, the brothers, we
could make, like you're saying, we could
make jokes with each other. And I saw
how in a nice way you could tease
someone about some um weakness they had,
you know, like, oh, you're getting into
that, you know, and it was done through
the heart. And in England, they could
take that. But when I went to Canada,
not at all. You know, my husband would
say to me, why are you being so mean to
me? You know, why why are you being so
aggressive? And I went, "Okay, okay."
But I I do remember one instant that I
was he's a ve he became in time um a
very light sleeper to the point that I
would be having to get up at night and I
would be so
quietly tiptoeing out of the room and he
would hear something and wake up and
like roar at me, you know, and I just
thought this is too much. And this went
on a few times and then I thought I felt
like I felt like mother saying to me,
"Okay, you have to make a joke out of
this, you know." So the next morning
he's perfectly normal. I went, "Oh, it's
you again. I had such a fright last
night in the bed, you know."
>> And he laughed and he laughed, you know.
So, so humor is is important and keeping
things, you know, so that you have
lightness as well, but it's also about
respect, isn't it? So what you're saying
is that the jokes they go too far and
it's not it's not
>> exactly it's it's uh I don't know I
really felt for this
my wife had a good subtlety that I
didn't have and I learned that through
our relationship this thing of even if
it's a joke even if it's innocent
somehow you need to have your attention
in Sasara and understand if it's the
right time or not even
>> but see that's what's so beautiful about
a balanced couple because she could see
that this was something in you that you
hadn't learned yet,
>> but she could see it. But in a nice way
together, you learn to, you know, you
learn through the B. And that's the
beauty that when you can see that that
you help each other
>> and that maybe you're learning some
things, you know, and he's not, but it's
like you said stages, you know. I I I
had to
>> Yeah, I had to change a lot in the
beginning. um partly because of things
that he couldn't handle. I could see,
you know, and so I thought, you know,
okay, I'll I'll I'll just have to
compromise on that or something, you
know, but then over time the, you know,
things things change and and that's what
I really wanted to share that you're on
a journey together and you have to be
patient with each other, you know, and
what you see at the beginning, you know,
you're first married and and you have
your lovely sort of, you know, six
months honeymoon period where you just
see the best in each other and hopefully
you will just you know let each other be
and enjoy and then Kunalini comes down
and starts working out in each other's
and you start to see oh okay he's doing
this or he's doing that you know it
doesn't mean that you have to correct
him
>> or that you have to change him but you
it's just like mother's going she's just
making you aware of that so that you can
be you know through your awareness and
understanding you can balance each other
you know and
um for example
so I shared this with you too before um
sometimes I would get quite emotional
something would happen would upset me
and and I had learned he was very calm
and he had a calming influence on me and
would help me make me feel better you
know
>> I remember I went to him I'm going Oh,
you know, and he went stop. He said,
stop. Go away. Come back when you're
more calm.
And I went, what? You know, but he was
absolutely, no, no, this is, you know,
too much. And and and I guess it was,
you know, I had not control of my
emotions. So, I just had to kind of
swallow and go. And it was really hard
in the beginning, you know, and I was
kind of very cross with him that he was
making me do this. But I went away and I
sort of, you know, big breaths and then
I came back and I just went
and then I said it very calmly and then
he was able to respond, you know, and
and and just say, "Why are you letting
this bother you?" You know, he had a way
of just saying things or, you know,
balancing when when I sort of learned to
see that this this this was his way of
of
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And also I know one thing that I
think could be very helpful for for
women is that I mean we're very extreme
we were quite extremely opposite my
husband myself and he um he didn't sort
of multitask and he and I would when I
would be asking him something or
explaining about something I would give
all the details you know oh this
happened this you know all the details
and finally he said just be short I
don't need all the details you know and
and of course again I would feel cross
you know like ah but I want to share all
the details you know then I know he's
got the full picture you know but but
then I realized that was it was
overwhelming him and he was just zoning
out you know just so so then I learned
okay he has a different kind of brain to
mine
>> and I'll just be to the point and and I
also learned that
>> I was used to being able to being
presented with a problem or something I
could immediately come up with solutions
or responses. But he didn't work like
that.
>> Yeah.
>> He like to absorb and to
>> you know have time and then so then I
learned okay just say what you want
briefly
and then come back let it sit with him
you know and then maybe the next day or
the day after I would just sort of
follow it up a little bit and then he
would just he would come back you know
and then I wasn't stressing him. I
wasn't causing him stress. So there's a
lot of adjustment, you know, in the
early years as you get to know each
other and and that's okay, you know,
because that's what
>> I think uh I mean you mentioned that I
think in in the episode of the wheel of
the wheels of the chariot to marry we
mentioned this a little bit but I think
what is important to understand is that
for certain things I mean of course
you're different type of couple
different type of people so doesn't
apply to everyone but let's say in
general with different degrees there are
different style of communications and
understanding reality because like all
the stories you just said is the same in
our marriage absolutely the exact same
like my wife will come to me it's like
okay let's have a brainstorming session
so she make a point and in the moment
she mention a point I'm already in my
brain thinking okay now how do I execute
this when do we go there you know I'm
I'm and then point number two number
three I'm wait I'm still at point one
I'm still trying to figure out how we do
point one. I'm like, we haven't finished
that. Let's the box. Let's stay in the
box.
>> And she just wanted to exactly say share
all the details in that. So, she had to
learn exactly be be more concise that I
always tell her just start from the end.
Start from the
>> point
to the point straight.
>> And I had to learn the opposite. So for
example now when she's um
>> she comes from work had a tough day this
and that she sits down and she's like oh
you know this guy did this or this
happened and immediately I'm like well
this is how you solve it do this do that
you should have done that and of course
that never works
>> versus now I just sit with I was like oh
tell me more what why did this person
and and she loves that but that is
something that I naturally would never
do in my life like it's just not in me
so I had to learn which button to press.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, to get the candy out of the
machine. And likewise, uh with me and I
think marriage is a lot of that is not
about what you feel more tuned into is
how can you learn about the other person
and adapt because in the moment you do
they will adapt to you
>> because they'll see the effort. It's
like a he did that for me. He you know
he didn't give me advice. He just
listened to me. How nice. Next time I'll
start from the end. I'll be because
>> No, that's it. Just get
>> exchange. It's an exchange, right?
>> But on this I must say and again last
time I feel in the will of the chariot I
tried to bring this point out. It didn't
really come across. I think in sah I
don't I don't want to be biased but I
think sometimes can be a bit harder for
your guineies and I'll explain why in
marriage
because
statistically if you see a different
things like for example women live more
longer right why because they have a
healthier life lifestyle they eat better
they they have a different type of like
not all of the women of the world but on
on trend you know they live about a
decade more than
uh look inside 70% of the new people
when you go to a program who is it is
women almost across every country they
have a natural attunement toward you
know meditation condalining this and
that then even you look within the
marriage at least in the couples I know
usually the the wife is always the one
that will try to do what is morally
right versus the husband will have a bit
more of a practical approach using that
so what you
have with all of these is a person
especially the wife that will have a
very high awareness of what's the right
thing to do and will try to use her
intuition to do so and then you have the
husband that is not inferior but just
works in a different way so I feel it's
can be quite difficult for the wife who
has these 50 things in her mind that she
wants to do and do things properly and
be morally oriented and this and that to
not nag the husband happened because
he's just there sitting on the couch.
Ah, you know, like I'm so good, you
know, and and she's like, "Come on, wake
up. We have to do this. We have to do
this. Look at the kids. They need this.
They need that." You know, and oh, or
you know that I see at least in my case,
the level of the expectation of
meditation and my wife was to bring to
the kids since there was more. So, it
was very high. You know, they are the
children of Shimaraj. We need to do
this. We And I was like, "Oh, come on.
They're kids. just let them be, you
know, go around
>> for my husband.
>> And you need both. You need both. It's
not like the man is inferior, but in the
dynamic of things because the wife is so
active and so morally oriented and
there's so much that she needs to cover.
There will be a tendency to criticize
because if I was in that position, I
will criticize all the time because I'm
like, I'm doing all this work. What are
you bringing to the table? Right? So,
and so I feel what you brought up today,
this advice that Shimani gave you, I
think is super important because I think
women in the family in Saj, they take a
very big portion of the work and they
are very involved and they're trying to
keep the expectations up here and and
and they have an expectation and
everybody else does it and the husband
is not always very reactive of
understanding of that and that sometimes
so I think on one end as in your case,
the the wife needs to be able to
sometimes even if you feel very angry,
upset to tone down, but the husband also
needs to become more reactive to the
needs and expectation that are again
usually morally driven of the wife.
>> But that that will happen and that takes
time. You know, I say to I say to young
people, you have to realize that your
husband has been a single person
>> and you can't switch overnight, you
know. I mean, as women, like you say,
we're a bit more tuned in to um but but
they've led a certain lifestyle and it
just takes some time. So, what you see
right right now
>> is not going to be like that for the
rest of his life. You know, you just
have to give him time so he can change
and see what you need in a nice way. And
I have to say that my husband was
completely totally resistant to any
advice or instruction or
absolutely
>> yes. So I had to learn.
>> Absolutely. So, just like you say, you
know, there would be things that needed
doing in the house and but if I went and
asked him or said to him, he would get
he would get annoyed, you know, and and
and when I think back,
>> he was I mean, it took a while for him
to get a stable job, you know, he was
trying to do different things. But once
he started working, he did that every
day from 8 to 5. He went every day and
he did that. And so he was all the time
in the vibrations of the outside world
you know and he would come home and I
would find it very difficult in the
beginning cuz my family in my family we
were talkers we shared about everything
you know you can ask someone my brother
we were just like open communication but
with my husband his family are different
he's learned a different way to
communicate and he felt overwhelmed you
know at times
>> and so one thing I learned which was
like a sort of brilliant idea mother
gave me was that so I would I in the end
I thought okay I'll make a list of what
we need you know things that need to be
done in the house and I'll put it on the
fridge and I just say these are things I
I feel like we need to do
>> and and I can't remember if I said if
you could do something that would help
or if I just left it but he understood
you know he understood and then he would
pick what he felt like doing at the
time, you know, and that just took a
whole level of aggravation out
>> and and I mean and you just have to
learn to accept that
>> they're not always going to do what you
would like them to do, you know, and and
in fact finally I reached a point and I
have to say it did take me quite a long
time um when I just let go of this need,
oh this needs to be done, this needs to
be done, you know, and and then I became
more relaxed. Okay, this is the list.
We'll just get to it when we can and do
that. And he became more relaxed and it
was just much much better.
>> Absolutely. No,
>> but this is this is all part of growing
in a marriage and growing in yourself in
learning what to let go of, you know,
what to let go. And one thing we
mentioned before um was that I learned
quite early on not to make a big deal
about the little things. save save your
conversation energy for something that's
more important you know like um shall I
tell the story about when I wanted to
send about sending to to Rome so
>> so we were um uh so we missed sending
Galama to Rome we were in Canada and we
didn't understand that they'd suddenly
all got too old and left and gone you
know gone to Switzerland so we was kind
of like well I think we should send
Shrea now or you know they were close in
age or we'll miss out because we were in
Canada there was like three other
children in the collective um very small
collective you know and you really
wanted them to have this and Shimadaji
had really um made this when she had
said about um I want you all to get
married and to have children she'd said
and I will build you a school I will
make you a school that you can send the
children to and they will go there and
you can go and be teachers and they will
be brought up there you know so we were
very um conscious that you know this was
important and so but I couldn't feel
vibrationally I just you know you
usually I would get a strong feeling oh
we should do this now you know like you
were saying this kind of moral compass
especially regarding the children and
what's good for them
>> and and and I learned you know I learned
that and I learned to trust that in
myself and I learned to understand like
you said that he didn't see things in
the same way you know and I I I was
saying before that we I went to the puja
the shri fatima puja in 1988 and shimati
gives a really amazing talk about
marriage about husbands and wives and
after that puja I felt like something
changed inside me and I I'd been kind of
trying to find my role you know like I
at that point I understood that my
husband is different from me. You know,
we don't always see eye to eye about
things
>> and and I didn't know I've always been
like a consiliator, you know, keep the
peace and I didn't know how to handle
this. And after this talk, it was like
mother gave permission. I felt it's okay
that we're different. That's okay. You
know, we don't always have to agree
about everything, but we do have to
sometimes compromise. It's like if
somebody one of us feels really
important about something, then the
other one, you know, that's what I
learned. Okay, this is really important
to him.
>> I'm going to have to let this go.
>> You know, later somehow this will work
out, but at this moment in time,
>> it's I'm not, you know, not going to
make an argument or a big confrontation
with let this go. This is super
important to him.
>> So, I learned that. So in this talk um
Shimaraji afterwards I felt I felt oh
that's my job my job is to look after
the dharma of the family and the
morality of the family. So if I see
something that I really feel is not good
for us morally then I can say something
that's okay to stand up for that because
that's my job you know. Exactly. Um so
it was a hugely um important
um thing. So I was just so I'll go back.
So so there we are. I can't feel should
we send Shre or not? You know and I
thought oh look I'm always making all
these decisions you know let me give him
a chance make him feel good about
himself. And so I said to him you know I
can't feel either way. Um what do you
think? What do you feel? And he said,
"Well, we don't really have the money."
And you know, we never did. I have to
say we never really ever had the money,
but sometimes you make a decision and
they come. And he said, "I I think it's
fine. You know, she'll stay here." So
the next morning, I finished my
meditation and as I bow down, I
immediately feel I'm bowing up. I feel
mother say to me, "Send shre to Rome."
And I went, "No, no,
>> how am I going to do this?" And I
thought how can I say to him you know it
was like the worst scenario
but it was so strong you know of course
I can't deny what
>> and at that time he wasn't particular
he's not somebody who feels vibration
you know like I get these in I feel
inside I can feel oh this is the right
thing
>> yeah and so so I had to I thought oh I
have to go and say this literally the
next day you
And so I went and and I said, you know,
I just had this experience in the
meditation. And he went, oh, you and
your experiences, you know, he was like,
what do you mean? He was really cross
with me. Really cross. And and I just so
I didn't say anything more, you know. I
I went away and I just kept saying to
mother, "How is this going to work out?
I don't know. How am I going, you know,
how how am I going to work? How is this
going to work out, mother?" you know,
>> and so I just sort of so I'd learned at
this time. So I just sort of left it for
most of the day and then I just kind of
said something like, you know, well, I
think we could do such and such, you
know, or I'm really sorry that it
changed, you know, but what what can I
do? And then it just sort of went on
like that for two or three days. And
then on the third day, and I didn't nag
at him. I didn't, you know, go on. I
literally surrendered it. Mother,
please, you help. I can't do this. You
have to work this out. The third day, he
just said, "Oh, all right. If you want
to send a sender like that, you know,
but it didn't matter, you know. He he'd
um you know, he'd come round." And so,
>> absolutely. So, it's really important
when I was talking to my daughter about
this, you know, we were saying how I
really wanted to do this podcast because
I felt that I don't feel like we're
giving enough support to people to
couples after they're married. you know,
there's a lot of challenges and things
and I felt like,
>> you know, maybe I could share some of my
experiences that might help people see
that it's, you know, it it has its
stages and you have you have your
suddenly things are going along nicely
and then suddenly something happens and
there's a bit of a drama and you know,
how do you get through those times?
>> Absolutely. and and she said to me and
this applies to everything the marriage
putting your name down
being matched making a decision getting
married through your married life she
said it's all about your connection with
Shrimat Gi said only Shrimat Gi knows
you and your husband your family and
your situation only she can give you the
help and the advice vice people other
people you know you can always listen to
what people say but ultimately it's only
who's there for you and I was I was in
Canada you know we got married went to
Canada five yogis in the ashram who just
got realization 3 months beforehand
and
you know things came up and I just had
to
deepen my relation relationship with
mother but she always came through for
me. I just you be surrendered, you'd be
detached. You may not get the answer
immediately. You may be washing the
dishes and suddenly oh ping you know oh
I could try it that way you know how do
I solve this this seems to be a conflict
I don't know what you know oh try it
this way
>> so
you can't underestimate
the power of your relationship with
Shrimati
how she's given us all these powers
especially as women we are much stronger
and deeper than We think and you grow
into it, you know, by having children,
having a family, you know, even through
all those hard difficult physical times
of being a mother, you get blessings,
you know, you get blessings and that
helps you, you know, through other
things. And we had after we've been
married about seven years, I remember
I can't remember what the details were,
but something happened. It's not like we
had an argument because I really didn't
argue, you know. I just motherthered
said don't argue so I didn't. I tried to
use vibrations and um it was important
for us to meditate together. That's the
biggest help. If you meditate together
every day once a week, we would do
pujas. Cuz when you meditate,
you somehow in that meditation, when
you're in sasara in the same room
together,
>> problems and things just get worked out.
We learned this in the ashram. We
learned that when you meditate regularly
every day together, things that could
become a big deal, somehow something
mother changes something within you and
and this works out.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, you know, that's a really big
support for you. But so, so here we are.
We're in this situation
and he says something
and it's like a deal breaker for me.
It's like,
>> wow. Suddenly this brick wall comes up
and I go, "How are we going to get past
this? I don't see how we can be married
like this. I can't and I cannot remember
what it was about." And I must have
prayed to mother because I always did
when it was a difficult thing. And I
just said, "Help me, mother. I don't
know what to do." And again, you know, I
just surrendered. I just let it be. And
then on the third day, he came and he
said something to me and I just realized
it's behind us. It all melted away and I
went,
>> "Yeah,
>> oh, it's not a big drama. It's not a big
deal. It's, you know, I mean, sometimes
husbands, I've learned I'm I've always
tried to be very honest and say what I,
you know, think the truth." But
sometimes, you know, he would just say
things that weren't there. Like when he
decided he said, "I'm never going to fly
on an airplane again." And I thought,
well, how's that going to work for us?
You know, and my daughter said, "Oh, no,
no, mom. Don't don't, you know, he just
said,
>> don't pay attention,
you know." So, so in one fell swoop,
this big thing that I thought was like
the end of the marriage, it just went,
you know. So, I really learned, you
know, mother said to me, don't make
dramas about things, you know, like just
and you really learned to witness. I
thought I was a patient person before I
got married. I thought I was a patient
person before I had children. Then I
discovered I wasn't a patient person at
all. And you have to learn, you know,
but all these things that you have to
change in yourself. All these things you
have to learn not to react to, you know,
how to become more detached. And it
takes time, you know, it's like mother's
and she keeps throwing up the same test.
Oh, you've not detached yet. You've not
done this, you know. and she throws this
up and then
>> but it makes you freer. You you let go
as you work out one thing. It's like oh
poof it's gone.
>> Yeah there is a something before that
you said that really made me laugh and I
think many many couples are like that.
Uh we are definitely one of those that
as you said if the wife will insist too
much on something the husband will go at
infinite lengths not to do it like at
incredible capacity to resist. I
remember there was the story is so funny
my wife is amazing because she's very
health conscious and food especially
especially since the kids were born so
good food fresh food this and that. I'm
from Italy. So, you know, hotel for
breakfast and, you know, eat whenever,
whatever, you know, very opposite words.
And there was a certain time that she
was nudging me a lot to, you know, oh,
don't eat so much bread, don't do this,
don't do that. And of course, I wasn't
having any of it. Zero. And it made
things worse. And once I was to I was
supposed to go to buy bread or
something. And uh preamble, I never
drink orange juice. It's not just
something that I I usually don't, you
know, but uh as I'm going out to buy
some bread,
she's telling me a story of something
that she read on Instagram of how orange
juice is a hulk and you know that they
is not real that you need it. You know,
something medical about how orange juice
is actually not needed. I've never
bought orange juice in my life.
I go to the supermarket just to buy
bread. I forgotten about the
conversation with her. I passed by the
the the the the drink pot and I said
this orange juice and all of a sudden it
looks so seducing. So I'm so thirsty. I
need orange juice. So it's orange juice.
I put it in the bag with the bread, you
know, and then I just open the door. I
go there and I forgot everything, you
know. And she looks at the back. She
looks at me like, "Are you kidding me?
Like you never bought oranges in your
entire life?" And I started laughing. I
was in tears because I saw it all. I saw
the dynamic. I knew what happened, you
know,
>> the drama, the
>> I didn't think about it. I just
subconsciously I was like, "Oh, you
don't want me to do it? I'm going to do
exactly that."
>> So, it was so funny because I could see
it, you know, and I was like laughing so
much about it.
>> Well, it's also it's like a little
trick, you know, that mother plays on
you. But I I think also you were talking
about you know talking together and
communicating
so often and I think you one has to be
really careful about this in marriage
that there are misunderstandings and
miscommunications because the husband
says something or does something and we
think from our experience that they're
doing it because of such and such. But
if you take the time to ask or talk and
understand, you find, you know, so
sometimes these little situations or
dramas come up because it's an
opportunity for us to understand each
other better. I'm I'm a little conscious
of of the time and I'm wondering I'm
wondering if if I should just briefly
talk about um the unusual wedding or did
you want do you we have time?
>> I would say yes. Uh
>> we can we can close with that. I think
we can close with the
>> Okay, I'll try to keep it a little bit.
>> Yes, if we can do in 10 minutes and
maybe I'll give a little introduction
because for those that have been
following us for years now. Couple of
years ago, we had a um an episode with
the marriage committee. It's called saj
marriages IMC and auntie Victoria and
uncle Marco were there and they
described this very rare occasion in
which Shimaraji
made the marriages in a complete
different way and it was very different
from what we actually have ever heard.
When I heard that story, I'm like, man,
this sounds insane. And then it stayed
in my mind, but I never met anyone
who was there. And then here comes
auntie who got married that year. So now
tell us the story.
>> So, so I went on India tour 1982 and so
I'll try to keep it short. Um, we were
I think we might have been near Verna.
So this is February. We're halfway
through the tour. Um February 14th,
something like that. And we're sitting
outside with Shamati.
Um you know, as we did all in front of
her and suddenly she says, "So what
about these marriages?" She said,
"Oh, I was just thinking that I wanted
to say I had put my name down because
>> I suddenly," so before I left in when I
was in England, suddenly something
changed in me and I felt, "Oh, I think
it's time to get married." Inside me, I
felt I felt like I've gone as far as
I've grown as a p single person.
individual
>> and and I felt I want to get married. I
want to have someone to love and look
after that and I I was and I felt at the
time I think I was a bit idealistic too
but I felt like I could love anybody you
know and so I put my name down. So there
I am sitting with Shamati Gi you know
here and she starts to talk about the
marriages and she said so I've been
getting I so I'm not I must say it I
can't say it like says
>> but she said she said I've been getting
some criticism
about
doing these matches and arranging the
matches. So this year I've decided you
can choose your p the person that you
want to marry. And I just went, "What?
No way. No way can I do that."
>> And so then she said, "Everybody
uh who wants to get married, please
stand up." So about I'd say out of a
tour of 82 people, 27 people stood up.
So 27 is not very many because there
were only like a dozen men in that list,
you know. So that's not a lot to choose
for. Or maybe a few more. There must
have been a few more. And then she said,
so then she talked about then people sat
down and then in turn they stood up and
she talked a little bit. She said
something about every single person who
had put their name on the list and or
who had wanted to get married. And
sometimes she said like, "Oh yes, um he
drives me around. He's a very good
driver." You know, generally everything
was very positive
>> positive. if somebody had well so for me
before me she got to Pam and she said oh
Pam such a beautiful heart such an open
heart I went oh yes that's what I would
like to hear and then she comes to me
and she says she says terrible left side
very weak left you know and I was just
like oh
and and then she counteracted as always
she balanced everything and she said Um
but not an aggressive bone in her body.
So sweet. And I thought, "All right, I
take that. I'll take that." You know,
>> yeah. So anyway, so so she went all the
way around and she said very lovely
things about about my husband, which was
nice, you know, and you have to
understand that she'd hardly met most of
those people she'd never met. She hadn't
met. They'd come on the tour, you know,
but she didn't know them. But yet she
did know them, you know. She knew
everybody. So then she said, "Now go
away and write down on a piece of paper.
Choose three names and write them on a
piece of paper and then you give them to
Warren." So I went away and I thought,
you know, I don't want to do this, but
mother said we have to do this. So So
then I started to think there was about
12 men I think on the list and I put my
attention in each one and I ah none of
these feel, you know, very good. And
then I got to my now husband and we'd
had a conversation in a group in a cafe
and I had felt at that time and I
remember saying some things and I
thought and then he said something else
I thought he doesn't understand me at
all. he doesn't get me at all, you know,
and he because he was interested in
talking about baseball and things and I
wanted to talk about deep emotional
things and, you know, stuff like that.
And so when I got to his name, I went,
"Oh, not compatible at all." You know, I
didn't even think about it was just
like, "Nope." You know, so then after
some struggling, I put three names down
and then I wrote, "I'm willing to travel
because I always felt I'd marry someone
else. I went from England." And I put,
"But I will marry whoever whoever
Shimadachi says I will marry. So then
all the names go in and then the next
day um Warren is coming in a little I
don't know rickshaw or car or something
and so he's coming into the camp and he
goes to different people you know and
you can see him my husband tells this
beautifully so you know he was like a
little sort of postman in a way and you
can see him going to all the different
people and having a little conversation
and then going away and and I thought
and I at that point I got cold feet and
I thought oh I'm not ready to get
married I can't you know I'll go and
tell him. So I was feeling very nervous
about the whole thing and so I went and
I said uh oh I want to take my name off
the list and he went oh actually
Shamad's found someone for you and I and
so immediately everything changed and
you go oh who is it and he said Richard
and I went Richard
so so I was you know understandably very
shocked but the nice thing was that it
was very innocent because I hadn't
thought about him or put attention on
it. It was like completely it was pure.
Yeah.
So
>> at at some point,
but I was still a bit confused, you
know. I mean, I trusted mother, but this
just felt like such opposite, you know,
so different.
>> And so he went off, you know, and then
he comes back again and he's sort of
beetling around and at some point I went
up and I said, I just wanted to know, is
Shumadaji happy with the match? And he
said, oh yes, yes, she's very happy. And
later I heard that she said that I was
very leftsided, he was very right-sided.
So it made it made a good match.
>> And she also said to him, if Listie says
no, I have someone else in mind for you.
You know, so I think it's really
important to remember that K K auntie K
said to me that Shadaji told her and I'm
sorry this is hearsay that there's a
good six different people who will make
a good match for you know so that
>> um we shouldn't feel like oh that was
the one I've lost the one or you know
>> it's not like that you know it's a lot
more it's just we have this romantic
idea of the soulmate You know exactly
it's not like that. Sahage marriage is
very normal. It's very normal you know
it's not like that. So
>> it's larger than our life also. It's
just larger than your Yeah.
>> Yeah. So then um so then we Oh yes. So
then Jamaraji said so there were I think
there were about so there were certain
number of matches maybe about eight or
10 and there were six re six matches of
people who'd come on the tour who were
already married before they came to
sajoga and they wanted to have a sahaj
marriage soi
said to us okay so you've accepted your
match now you can only talk two minutes
each day that's it two minutes you
Oh my goodness. So I could see this was
so that people's egos didn't come up and
you start thinking about, oh, this is
not good match, you know, like that. You
really worked hard to try to help us
>> not to think about it too much, you
know.
>> So then
we were standing in the dinner queue. So
it didn't mean you couldn't So I figured
it didn't mean you couldn't be with
them, you just couldn't talk to them,
you know. So we're standing in the
dinner queue and I'm standing behind him
and sudden and so at this point so
because when I heard that Chimadichi was
happy with the match I just surrendered
completely. I just went, "Okay, it's
fine. This is great. This is a match. I
don't understand why it's a good match,
but you know, that's fine." And
I was just really surrendered and opened
my heart. And then, you know, we did
talk a little bit and you start by being
together, you get a sense, you know, you
can feel their spirit, you feel them as
a as a being. So, it's very beautiful
when you're not actually talking because
you're feeling the essence of the person
and he was very light and joyful and he
was funny. He made me laugh, you know,
um nice things like this and I could
feel so when we were together standing
in that queue, I felt comfortable
together. I felt actually a bit safe,
you know, I felt safe with him and she
said that later, you know, I thought he
would make you feel secure, which was so
sweet, you know, these lovely things. So
I'm standing there in the queue behind
him just enjoying being there you know
waiting we're in the dinner queue and
then suddenly I felt like mother say
inside of me you are two halves of the
same coin one of you is the heads one of
you is the tails and together you make a
whole
>> wow
>> and I felt her say inside his strengths
are your weaknesses your strengths are
his weaknesses so together you will help
each other and and then I felt her say
deep things.
What did she say? It was like little
things you can talk to each other about
and change. You know, superficial
things, but deep things will take time
and you have to let that go, you know.
And that was such good advice because I
could see that you know especially in
the first year year of marriage I could
see that there were like deep I wouldn't
say personality thing things that he was
just ways of behaving you know that he'd
grown up in his family and this is why
they were do doing things and that and
there was no point to try and talk about
them because he wasn't aware of them you
know he didn't think that was anything
wrong and and in and in a lot of ways
you It it wasn't wrong. It was just
different. And then and then I felt
mother say to me superficially on the
outside
you are very different but inside you
have the same like moral core you know
sense of and and that's very true that
about deep things you know we've always
been on the same page about dharmic
things and you know what's important in
the family with the children and things
like that. we've always been on this and
and also how you relate to people
outside you know about honesty and um
and just respect and you know those
things so all those important things but
outside she said you know you've had
different I felt her you know saying you
had different upbringings different
families and his family was totally
different to mine they were actually a
blessing a complete blessing but um you
know so and she said gradually those
outside things will drop way and you
will come into the center together. And
that's exactly what happened. And it
took time and the rough things, you
know, worked out and rubbed off. And
just by being together and living
together and going through your little
tests or your little dramas, you just
become closer. And every time you have
like some big challenge and you work
through it and you come through the
other side, even if it's a bit
uncomfortable or there's some not happy
words, you know, it creates a deeper
bond. It creates a deeper bond. So, you
shouldn't be afraid of challenges or
afraid of, you know, tests. It's all
part of weaving you both together. and
we and because of what mother had said
also about the children as soon as we
got married um I just and I could feel
you know we're very different this is
going to take a while to sort of sort
ourselves together and I felt her you
know we both agreed we're going to have
children straight away and and really
that all our generation did that because
this is what you know mother's waiting
for them to grow up so get on with it
you know have have the children and the
other thing that she said to me one time
um she came to the airport. She would
always say to me when she saw when we,
you know, met, she'd come to Canada and
she'd say, "And how are you?" You know,
for years she'd say to me, "And how are
you?" And often at the time, early on, I
wasn't feeling good inside. But you
learned, you always said, "I'm fine,
mother." You know, and she knew you
weren't, but you know, that's what you
were supposed to say. And then one one
time she came and the children must have
been like, you know, six and five or
something. And and I was feeling good.
That was actually like a lot of this
stuff through living in Canada, being
married to my husband, it had just
really worked out so much in the left
side without me trying, just by being
there, you know, it worked out. And she
I was standing next to my husband and we
had the children and she comes and she
says um she started talking to him and
she said, "And where's Felicity?" You
know, I'm right next to him and she
knows me, but where's Felicity? You
know, and then she then I said, "Oh, I'm
right here, man." and she goes, "I knew
the children would work it out, you
know."
>> Oh, sweet.
>> So, you know, I mean, that was the whole
point. You you you know, she sent us
these beautiful little souls and they
change us, you know, they they change
our lives. And I do want to say because
I've said so many not necessarily
complimentary things about my husband,
but you know, oh, what a really special
person, you know, he turned he he was
and he And when we were having difficult
times sometimes and I just feel like oh
I you know I I I'd be crying. I have to
say I'd be crying on my own you know
>> and then I I I just suddenly thought I'm
where's the photo? Where's that photo of
him? And I had this photo of him when he
was a bit younger before we were
married. And he's just so sweet and pure
and innocent and joyful. And I just went
this is who I married. This is the
spirit. this is the spirit of my husband
and all this other stuff is nothing.
It's just going to go away, you know.
And that sort of helped me to just sort
of hold on to things. And I was far
away, you know, we had very few people
in the collective. I didn't really have
people except for his mom who wasn't a
Sajobi to, you know, help or support me.
And but I had mother, you know, and so
to to people who say, "Oh, but you
always had mother with you to help you
through all these things."
>> I didn't. She wasn't there, but she was
there for me inside. So, I really want
people to understand that that you're
not alone in your marriage. Sometimes
you feel like that. Sometimes you feel
very confused and you know and the what
my husband was so as we spent more time
together I could see his really
beautiful qualities which were very
different from me. But I could also see
things that at the time I felt were
weaknesses or you know not such good
things.
But over the years as we got older and
now we're retired, all the things that I
thought were kind of weaknesses are
actually really positive pluses. And
he's made my life as a retired person,
you know, living back in England such a
joy. You know, I don't think I I could
do that. So, you know, it's really when
you're married, you're in for the the
long haul. You should be in for the long
haul. And you can't see the bigger
picture at the beginning. You know, you
can't see the perspective. And I think I
I I'm grateful that we had those
experiences with Shumadachi where she
really established in us that these
marriages also aren't not just for you
personally. You know, I had wanted to
share what is a sahaj marriage. So sahaj
sah sah sahaj marriage is different from
a regular marriage because it's for your
evolutionary growth because it's for our
spiritual path and the way the matches
happen is you are not only matched
vibrationally with opposites but
culturally
>> the culture the culture is a big thing
you know and I when we after 18 months
We went back and lived in England for 18
months. And I think that really helped
us because my husband could see I wasn't
just this weird person who liked to wear
floral clothes and have florals flowers
everywhere, but I was actually English
and in England that's what they liked
and that's what they did, you know. So I
think it really gave him a better
understanding of me. He didn't make so
many jokes about me and my classes after
that. And I so I think and also if you
go and you spend time with the family
each person's family then you also
understand where they're coming from you
know and it just when you understand it
gives you more compassion. So when you
have a reaction try to think well why is
he doing this you know where is this
coming from and why am I reacting why am
I reacting I shouldn't be reacting I
asked shamadaji one time very early on
>> every time I kept finding I was having
like critical thoughts about or
judgmental thoughts or thinking just
thoughts about other people and she said
to me why is your attention on other
people why isn't your attention on
yourself and And I think that applies
for marriage too. You know, why are you
worrying about him or what he's saying
or what he's doing? Just concentrate.
You know, just be the best you can be.
So anyway, you know,
>> I just wanted to say, you know, that
>> Oh, and the last thing about Sahage
marriages is it's not just for us. It is
for the collective. It is for the
changing of humanity. And I was very
conscious of that. And I remember one
time when I was crying to myself and I
kept feeling you know what if I can work
this out in our marriage then this will
help all those other marriages and
Shamadajid said to us that each person
in sajoga works out for 10,000 others.
That's what she said. So this this
monkey see monkey do you know as it
works out for you it spreads this ripple
effect for other people. So I that
helped me to see the bigger picture and
to understand how by matching people
from different cultures and different
backgrounds that we create this
beautiful new alliance. you know, in one
spell swoop, all our personal baggage,
our conditionings are just cut like
that, you know.
>> And as we were saying before, the the
only the two things that usually that we
had conflicts about for was money
>> and parenting styles. Parenting styles.
Yeah. And you just have to work that
out. You just have to, you know, I came
from a very strict background. uh very
critical you know background uh also
very loving but that and my husband came
from an incredibly loving totally
non-judgmental background when I was
with his mother and I went I said to him
you grew up in a family like this I
can't believe it where people actually
nice to each other all the time and
because my you know and and I remember
being with his mom and feeling
unconditional love from her
>> and I thought I thought this this is
this is what it feels like to be loved
and not judged and it made me want to be
the best person you know it made it's
like with inadji's presence she she just
focused on you and on your spirit and it
lifted you it elevated you into being a
better person into highlighting all the
good qualities you are she didn't bother
with for the negative stuff, you know,
unless it was, you know, you were
sobbing or crying or something, you
know.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, and it goes back to what she
said to that leader, don't focus on the
negative, you know, just let it come up
and it will I'm working it out. It will
go away, you know, just focus on the
positive. And I think if you can do that
and trust yourself that you can work
this out, you know, mother's giving you
all the tools, it may take a little
time, you know, and marriage goes in
stages. I definitely felt after seven
years like, oh, we've crossed a lot of
bridges now. And 15 years, I remember
feeling or 16 years, I remember feeling,
wow, I think we've really learned about
each other and adjusted and all these
things, you know. And then when we got
to 20 years and we had a wedding
anniversary party at the ashram and we
took all this food and it was very love
and I felt I just felt so high on
vibrations and I remember feeling like
why what am I feeling? Why I'm feeling
so special and loved and I just want to
give joy to everyone. And I suddenly
felt like,
it's very hard to explain this in words,
but I felt like that I had somehow
accumulated boons and blessings from,
you know, sticking it out and not I
shouldn't say sticking it out, but just
staying with it, you know, staying with
it and and being there for it. And and I
have to say that, you know, my husband,
bless him, I was the one that would take
all the kids to the the schools and I,
you know, I was the kind of the active
one in a way, you know, and it would
have been we never had much money and
but he he went to work every day. He
stuck in that job and he was a complete
support when we ran that Vancouver
Sahage School for three years. He was
like bottom of the of the list, you
know. It was like the school came, the
kids came first, the school came first
and and if he was lucky, I could had a
bit of time for him. He never
complained. I remember saying to him,
"I'm really sorry, honey." You know, and
he said, "No, this is what's important.
The children need this, you know, and
but you don't see that when you're first
married. You're not in that situation.
You don't know how he's going to come
up, what's the word? He's going to rise
up to the occasion and be there for
these things that you you need." So, I
just can't say enough, you know, be
patient, give it time. I know not always
all marriages work, but a lot I've seen,
you know, sometimes fall apart and you
feel like, oh, I think if they'd had a
bit more support, you know, um, you
know, mother could have talked to them
or something, she would have helped them
see them through. So anyway, I just want
to give all my love and support to all
the couples coming up and just try not
to it's hard because it's a very it's an
important thing in your life, but it
will work out. If it doesn't work out
the first time or the second time, it
will work out and just stick in there
and it, you know, after how many 43
years of marriage, it's a lot of joy. We
still sometimes, you know, get a bit
annoyed with each other, but that's
okay. You know when you've been I mean
that's that's the thing I was thinking
this in meditation today that that first
year is really important to make each
other feel loved you know I was very
aware that my husband was a little bit
insecure you know and that I had to so
you don't nag you don't criticize you
don't have these long park bench
conversations about what they're doing
wrong or what they should be doing you
know just enjoy just enjoy let mother
work it out. Anyway, I know I've said
way too much, but hopefully that will
>> No, it was lovely. Auntie was
>> No, no, it's been two hours.
>> Oh, I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry.
>> This is This might be like the longest
episode so far, but
>> I did say I had problems not, you know,
>> I think it's fine actually to to
support. I just feel that we really need
you know there's always up to the
wedding and then what about after the
wedding you know mother said that she
wished somebody would write books about
you know in the marriage being married
and all the nice things and you know
advice so so this is a little bit to
help but I'm sure other you know there's
lots of other people who could share and
be supportive and and and and not to
feel like what you said fatim about Not
uh sorry Fabby about not um not
>> fatty matrates. No, no, no, no. It's
because we have this lovely Turkish yogi
in Vancouver called Fatty, you know. So,
my brain is programmed to say fatty, not
fabby. Um,
>> oh, what was I going to say? That's
gone.
>> Never mind.
Never mind. Enough said. Enough said.
Well, thank you for having me on for so
long. Maybe you can do it in two parts.
I don't know.
>> Yeah. No,
>> let's see.
It's actually one one and a half maybe
one and 40
>> because we talked for like 20 30 minutes
before
>> exactly.
>> So I think that we can wrap it up. Thank
you very much auntie h for the insight
for the experiences and I think people
will actually find it really really
interesting also because you mentioned
the stories which reminded you quite a
lot which it which is like what we were
actually aiming for. So especially me as
I as I asked you like the last time we
>> we had a chat.
>> So I don't know if uh Fabit has to say
anything or we can just close it.
>> I was just so I remember now what I
wanted to say was to um don't be afraid
to ask for help like you can ask someone
I'm confused you know this is happening.
We don't want to hear a lot of
complaints. You know, that's not good
for you. But if but ask, you know,
there's nothing wrong with just saying,
"I'm confused. You know, I don't
understand this or that." And I'm sure
you'll find lots of aunties, you know,
>> there for you. We're all rooting for
you. We're all rooting for you.
>> Yes. It's important. It's a collective
marriage. It's something that the
collective should support. And if you
have any doubts beforehand, please say
no. Don't go through with the marriage.
You know, if you're crying on the day,
there is something wrong. It's not going
to get better after you get married. If
you've got doubts and you still get
married, the negativity is just going to
work on your doubts, you know, and it
it's it's really hard. You my my feeling
is that you should feel comfortable to
with each other. you have that faith
that you know mother has this is a good
match and then that will guide you
through.
>> Yeah.
On on this beautiful note thank you so
much auntie I like le said I really
enjoyed also hearing how it evolved at
the beginning and how there were few
matches and then it got more and more
structured you know and this particular
experience you had. It was very very
very loving. I'm sure everyone is going
to like it. So for good Lily, thank you
so much auntie. And sorry that I
disappeared. My computer died at some
point. So I'm I'm joining with the phone
now. Probably the audio is not so good.
>> No, actually it was really funny to see
you from the phone camera. So thank you
everyone for for listening. This was
Sahhat Times podcast. Thank you very
much auntie. Thank you very much Fabri.
>> Good good evening. Have a good night.
Bye.
[Music]